Regulating our emotions isn't always easy.
It's hard not to be overwhelmed when we're stressed,
lash out when we're angry,
or feel defeated when we fail.
But by boosting your self-regulation,
you can control your emotions,
rather than letting them control you.
It's a useful skill, so let's take a look
at the elements of self-regulation
and how you can improve your self-regulation skills.
First, self-regulation is made up of five elements.
To start, there's self-control,
which is your ability to control your feelings.
With high self-control,
you can remain rational and levelheaded,
even when your emotions are running high.
Second, there's trustworthiness.
When you regulate your emotions,
you're less likely to act impulsively.
You act consistently and according to your values,
and that helps others trust your behavior.
Third, there's conscientiousness,
which is about being disciplined and responsible.
Rather than blaming external factors for your actions,
you take responsibility for your performance.
Fourth, there's a adaptability,
which refers to how well you handle
change and unexpected stress.
Without this quality, you may crack under pressure
or express high anxiety, stress, and worry.
And finally, there's innovation.
With strong self-regulation,
you're more likely to see challenges as opportunities,
and be open to new, innovative ideas.
So, how can you improve your self-regulation?
Rather than avoiding your feelings,
you'll need to confront them head-on.
Here are five tips.
The first tip for improving your self-regulation
is to prepare for the emotion.
If you need to walk into a tough conversation,
or you know you have a challenging day ahead,
think about how you can calm yourself down
before that event.
Prepare for your emotional reactions,
and you'll be less likely to get caught off-guard.
Second, practice mindful observation.
Rather than burying your feelings,
mindfully accept them.
Recognize why you're feeling the way you are,
and don't judge that emotion.
Third, take time to STOPP,
which is an acronym that stands for stop, take a breath,
observe, pull back, and proceed.
When your emotions are spinning,
pause, breathe in, observe how you're feeling,
and take a step back before responding.
Then, once you've evaluated that bigger picture,
proceed with the most appropriate action.
Fourth, practice letting go.
When we hold onto negative emotions,
we often escalate our sensitivity to them.
So, instead, try to recognize
that something happened,
feel grateful for what you've learned,
and then think toward the future.
Finally, reframe your thoughts
through cognitive reappraisal,
which involves readjusting your mindset.
Whether you're stuck in traffic,
dealing with an unfocused employee,
or feeling disrespected, there are a lot of ways
to interpret the same situation.
And with cognitive reappraisal,
you can choose the healthiest interpretation
by changing your thought patterns.
So, the next time your emotions are running high,
remind yourself that you're in control.
Remember these tips, and you can improve
your self-regulation skills
and stay in the emotional driver's seat.